<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Sad memorials of the royal martyr, or, A parallel betwixt the Jewes murder of Christ and the English murder of King Charls the First being a sermon preached on the solemnity of His Majestie's martyrdom in the Cathedral-Church of Sarum, An. Dom. 1669 / by T.L. ...</title>
            <author>Lambert, Thomas, 1616-1694.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1670</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 65 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A48660</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L244</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R8199</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12922460</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12922460</idno>
            <idno type="VID">95422</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A48660)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 95422)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 387:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Sad memorials of the royal martyr, or, A parallel betwixt the Jewes murder of Christ and the English murder of King Charls the First being a sermon preached on the solemnity of His Majestie's martyrdom in the Cathedral-Church of Sarum, An. Dom. 1669 / by T.L. ...</title>
                  <author>Lambert, Thomas, 1616-1694.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 33 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Tho. Milbourn for Robert Clavel ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1670.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Thomas Lambert. Cf. BM.</note>
                  <note>Probably preached Jan. 30, 1670.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
                  <note>Marginal notes.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Charles --  I, --  King of England, 1600-1649 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:95422:1"/>
            <p>SAD MEMORIALS OF THE Royal Martyr: OR, A Parallel betwixt the <hi>Jewes</hi> Murder of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Murder of KING <hi>Charls</hi> the Firſt: BEING A SERMON Preached on the Solemnity of His <hi>Majeſtie</hi>'s Martyrdom. In the Cathedral-Church of <hi>Sarum,</hi> An. Dom. 1669.</p>
            <p>By <hi>T. L.</hi> (M. A.) Prebend of the Cathedral Church of <hi>SAR<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>M.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>;</p>
               <bibl>Jo. 19.15.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Tho. Milbourn</hi> for <hi>Robert Clavel,</hi> and are to be Sold at the <hi>Gun</hi> in <hi>Ludgate-Street,</hi> 1670.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:95422:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:95422:2"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>WHo is there that doth not obſerve, that store and abundance is an uſual means to depreciate any thing; and that that which is moſt frequent is generally moſt ſlighted; as Common-ways are moſt trodden and trampled on: ſo that there is no very great cauſe to wonder, that <hi>Iſrael</hi> it ſelf ſhould then loath <hi>Manna,</hi> when Manna lay in heaps in the Camp; or that they ſhould grow weary of Angels-food, when Angels-food was their conſtant diſh. And truly, this is as viſible in this preaching-Age, wherein (to the diſcredit of this Nation be it ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken) I know not whether is greater, the induſtry of the Preachers to convince, or, the induſtry of the Hearers not to be convinced of their wickedneſs. And therefore when there is on one hand a plenty to ſatiate, and, on the other, corrupt humours in the Patients to make that Diet become nauſeous; it may be admired what there could be, to invite me to put ſuch a thing as a Sermon, into the ſight of the World. I muſt confeſs, had there not been ſome
<pb facs="tcp:95422:3"/>other kinde of inducements, beſides the good opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of that City for whom it was compoſed, and of that Congregation to whom it was preached; I ſhould hardly have inclined to have publiſhed ſo plain and unpoliſhed a Diſcourſe. But this I muſt ſay, that I look on that place as a Society of the greateſt Loyalty and candor in the whole King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and conſequently (although they have alſo their ſhare in the guilt) that moſt places of this Nation, have much more to anſwer for, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent of, in relation to the Blood of the Royal Martyr King <hi>Charls</hi> the Firſt, than they; And I cannot doubt but that the ſame Spirit of God that made thoſe ſo paſſionately reſent this Charge laid on them, may make the Sermon, now it is written, become that to others, that it was to them when it was preached. But one thing it was above all that tempted me to this courſe, and that is, The Hint that I have given of a great and Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional ſin and infelicity, that hath too generally paſſed without any notice or obſervation; and that is, the unconſcionable careleſneſs or grounds on which the People of this Kingdom trifle away the peace and ſecurity of the Church and State, in popular Elections; ſometimes inconſiderately ſiding with impoſing Landlords, ſometimes as raſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly running with an unwary rabble, to depute in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufficient, and many times ill-principled Perſons to be their Repreſentatives in the great Councel of this Kingdome; from whom what can be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected to come, but deſperate and miſchievous, or at the beſt, crude and immature Counſels. Of
<pb facs="tcp:95422:3"/>what conſequence this very thing is to our per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petual Peace, or Diſtractions, I believe no diſcreet Perſon can doubt; and I ſhall amply obtain my deſire, if any ingenuous and well affected Perſon that hath the leaſure, ſhall ever take the hint, and beſtow on his Countrey, a juſt Diſcourſe and ſtate of the caſes and obligations that lye on all Perſons, and Societies, to make conſcience of their proceedings in an Affair of this Importance. For I think, if ſome courſe be not taken to awaken the common People, to conſider what they ought to do, and to repreſent unto the preſent <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> in what condition ſeveral Corporations ſtand by means of many diſaffected Perſons re admiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion into thoſe Societies, out of which for diſloy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty they were within this ſix or ſeven Years caſt; All the courſes that this great and loyal Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel ſhall take to ſecure our proſperity will ſignifie nothing; but that, on the calling of new Councels (which will ſurely be for the moſt part anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to ſuch Mens intereſts, paſſions, and Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples) all ſhall be immediately battered down, and demoliſhed; and within this ten or twenty Years, this Nation muſt infallibly come into the ſame state and condition, that it was in, <hi>Anno 1642.</hi> For although they take the ſame strict and ſolemn Oaths, and are admitted under the ſame conditions and ſubſcriptions that other Men are, yet I appeal to all men living that have opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity to obſerve their actings, whether they make any conſcience at all of vow-breach and perjury; and whether they become not the ſlie, if not the
<pb facs="tcp:95422:4"/>open countenancers of all the factions and ſedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Perſons in the Nation. Nor do I think that any prudent Man that hath his Eyes abroad with him, can chooſe but ſee, how the ſottiſhneſs and poverty of ſome places and Perſons make them eaſie to be impoſed on, and neither think nor care whom they elect to <hi>Parliament;</hi> and how the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and purſe of others, make them as active and powerful to pervert ſuch Electors. And is not this of a ſad conſideration, that little Feaſts and entertainments, or little fears or brow-beat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, ſhould engage the majority of Burroughs for this or that Perſon, whatever his principles or qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifications are; and conſequently that the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations of our Laws ſhould be laid on Rundlets of Wine, on Barrels of Ale, or on the humours of diſcontented Fanaticks? Is it not a miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble thing, that thoſe that are honeſt and peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Men, ſhould be ſlack and negligent of ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing at Elections, when to be ſure the turbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent and ſeditious ſhall be induſtrious and eager? I think we ought to remember, that as our ill choice hath heretofore drawn ſo great ſins and vengeances on our heads, ſo our more faithful and careful Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, are the only means to ſecure and perpetuate our peace and proſperity, and to keep us from ſuch ſins, from ſuch ſhames, and from ſuch miſeries; which ſhall for ever I hope be both the Prayer and ſerious endeavour of my conſiderate Reader, and my ſelf. More than this, we cannot wiſh; and leſs than this, our affection to our Native Countrey can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not exact at our hands.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:95422:4"/>
            <head>SAD MEMORIALS OF THE <hi>ROYAL MARTYR,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Act. ij. the xxxvij. and part of the xxxviij. Verſ.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Now when they heard this, they were pricked in their hearts, and ſaid unto <hi>Peter,</hi> and to the reſt to the Apoſtles, Men and Brethren, What ſhall we do?</p>
                  <p>Then <hi>Peter</hi> ſaid unto them, Repent. —</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T hath been often my extream won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to conſider the different effects of the Apoſtles preaching to the firſt Chriſtians, and of our preaching to the laſt Chriſtians; the eaſineſs and ſeriouſneſs of their repentance, and the difficulty
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:95422:5"/>and perfunctorineſs of ours; how eaſily their eyes melted into Tears, and how much more readily our hearts turn into Rocks: and yet all this while, there are the ſame crying ſins; the ſame glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Goſpel; the ſame light within us, our rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and conſcience; and the ſame impulſe from without, the Holy Spirit of God; Religion hath ſtill the ſame Embaſſy and Miniſtration; the World hath the ſame needs; Vice and Sin hath the ſame baſeneſs; the Rule hath the ſame per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection; and the Holy Ghoſt hath the ſame ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficacy. But I conceive the reaſon of the ſo great difference ariſeth principally from theſe two things. 1. <hi>From the different temper of the hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers then, and now.</hi> 2dly. <hi>From the different way of working, preaching, and miniſtration then, and now.</hi> As for the temper of the Primitive hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, this is certain, They were more ſimple, ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and ſincere; Religion to them was a thing in earneſt; the intereſt of their Souls, and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal ſalvation or everlaſting Death, was that which their hearts had a moſt awful regard to; and you meet not the ſowreſt knot, the moſt neglectful unbeliever among them, but when theſe things were urged, his heart was ſmitten with conſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation and amazement; From which, neither glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, nor riches, nor throne, nor honour, nor tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bunal could ever ſhelter him. <hi>St.</hi> Peter<hi>'s</hi> preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, wounds the <hi>Jews;</hi> and at <hi>St.</hi> Paul<hi>'s</hi>
               <note n="(a)" place="margin">Act. 24.25.</note> 
               <hi>preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> Felix <hi>trembled.</hi> As for the heartineſs and ſincerity in the Converts, two things there are that put it out of all queſtion; the firſt is,<note n="(b)" place="margin">Act. 4.34.</note> 
               <hi>The
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:95422:5"/>devoting of their whole Eſtates to the ſervice of the Church and Religion;</hi> and the other is, Their free and penitent<note n="(c)" place="margin">cap. 19.18.</note> 
               <hi>confeſſion of their ſins.</hi> And without all controverſie, He that forſakes this Worlds good, that gives up his Eſtate for Religion, and the Kingdom of God's ſake; and that confeſſeth his faults with tears in his Eyes; is in earneſt. On the contrary, the Hypocriſie of our Religion is made as conſpicuous, in that we are ſo far from parting with any thing to religious, or charitable uſes, that we pant after the Eſtates that are ſo given by others, and are ſo far from being aſhamed of profaneneſs and impiety, that we<note n="(d)" place="margin">Eſa 3.9.</note> 
               <hi>boaſt and proclaim our ſin</hi> as <hi>Sodom,</hi> and make our<note n="(e)" place="margin">Phil. 3.19.</note> 
               <hi>glory of that which is indeed our ſhame.</hi> The ſecond difference, the different way of preaching, and miniſtration be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween them and us, is as viſible and conſpicuous. We want that heroical Spirit, and courage in the cauſe of God, that plainneſs, and zeal in our Miniſtration, that they always uſed; they called <hi>inceſt Inceſt,</hi> and <hi>murder Murder</hi> without mincing of crimes; they moſt ſharply reproved where the ſins were great; their hearts were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all baſe deſpondencies; they neither fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the frowns of Greatneſs, nor the tumults of the Multitude, but ſpake out with all ſeverity; they were not ſo weak to imagine that the moſt head-ſtrong Beaſt was to be beſt managed with the looſeſt Rain; No, they pleaded the cauſe of God with rigour and ſharpneſs, as we may ſee in St. <hi>Stephen</hi>'s diſcourſe with the <hi>Jews:</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:95422:6"/>Act. 7.51, 52. <hi>O ye stiff-necked and uncircumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in Heart, and in Ears, ye do always reſiſt the Holy Ghoſt; As your Fathers did, ſo do ye; Which of the Prophets have not your Fathers per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted? and they have ſlain them which ſhewed before, of the coming of the juſt One, of whom ye have been now the betrayers and murderers.</hi> They feared not life, they could not debaſe themſelves to ſoothing and flattery, becauſe Faw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning became Doggs, better than Shepheards. On the contrary, we deal with ſmooth Hands, and oily Tongues; we reprove with Figurative wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons; we uſe Metaphorical conviction only, and then our hearers think that they have nothing to anſwer for, but metaphorical ſins, and why ſhould it then be thought ſtrange, that we ſhould work nothing in them, but a metaphorical repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. We imagine we have well performed our duty, when we have done it neatly, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive ſin is duly chaſtiſed, when our hearers think that we do not mean them. Believe me, Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren; I have too much affection for my people, and particularly for this Aſſembly, to deal ſo treacherouſly with you, but am reſolved, that I ſhall then have beſt performed the office of this Day, when I ſhall have left this glorious Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr's Memory in your minds, as a Miracle of Men, as a Mirrour of Princes, and convinced you that <hi>Charls</hi> his Blood was enough to ſink a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and the leaſt drop of it to damn this whole City. 'Tis the repentance of the guilty I ſeek, and if any Man be diſcontented at this, I have
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:95422:6"/>but little cauſe to be troubled at it, If I can pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce peace to my ſelf.<note place="margin">Ezek. 3 19.</note> 
               <hi>Liberavi animam me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am. I have freed mine own ſoul.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Apoſtle's Charge on his Auditory, is couch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the 22. and 23. Verſes of this Chap. <hi>Ye Men of Iſrael, hear theſe words, JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zareth, a Man approved of God amongst you by Miracles, Signs, and Wonders, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ch God did by him in the middeſt of you, as ye your ſelves alſo know, Him have ye taken, and by wicked hands have crucified and ſlain.</hi> I will but a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry-little vary the words, and lay the very ſame Charge on the greateſt part of this Aſſembly. <hi>Ye Men of this City, hear theſe words; CHARLS the Firſt, King of England, a Man approved of God amongst you, by a juſt and righteous Title unto theſe Kingdoms, by a Princely clemency, by an incomparable piety, by a moſt innocent and a vertuous life; by a flouriſhing eſtate which God wrought by him in the middeſt of you, as ye your ſelves alſo know; Him have ye by rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and treacherous hands delivered and taken, and in a moſt barbarous and cruel manner mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered and ſlain.</hi> The leaſt that can be ſaid of this Wickedneſs, is this, that it is a publick and a National Sin, and cannot be expiated, but by a publick and a National Repentance; And this the ſervice of this Day confeſſeth, <hi>where we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>precate this Blood from our ſelves and poſterities for ever.</hi> But becauſe you will never be able to proportion your grief as you ought, till you have a full ſight of your guilt. I ſhall endeavour to
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:95422:7"/>make you more ſenſible of that, by paralleling the Sin that is before us, of Murdering King <hi>Charles,</hi> with this Hiſtory of the <hi>Jews</hi> murder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of <hi>Chriſt:</hi> Nor do I find in the whole Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture any Caſe ſo neer alike as this. We read indeed in ſome places of great Calamities, and in ſome too of calamitous Deaths, that have fallen on many eminent Perſons; and of ſome that have dyed for Righteouſneſs ſake, as<note n="(g)" place="margin">Mat. 14.10.</note> 
               <hi>John the Baptiſt,</hi> by <hi>Decollation for reproving Herod,</hi> but he was a Prophet, not a Prince;<note n="(h)" place="margin">Act. 7.59.</note> St. <hi>Stephen stoned to Death,</hi> but he was a Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple, not a King; <hi>Saul was a King,</hi> and he dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Sword, but he neither lived a good life, nor dyed by the hands of others; <hi>David was a king,</hi> and yet <hi>a man of great Sorrows,</hi> a Type of Chriſt Himſelf; and yet, although he was a <hi>Confeſſor,</hi> he was no <hi>Martyr,</hi> but dyed in his Bed. But now, The Murder of King <hi>Charls</hi> is like the Murder of our Lord <hi>Jeſus Chriſt:</hi> in ſeveral Relations and reſpects; only let it be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred that Chriſt was a ſpiritual Saviour too, and, ſo, far beyond all Earthly Princes: becauſe<note n="(i)" place="margin">Mat. 14.33.</note> 
               <hi>he was the Son of God, as well as the Son of Man;</hi> However, if we ſhall ſee that this hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible wickedneſs, is much of the ſame nature, with the murder of theſe execrable <hi>Jews,</hi> you'l have the ſame reaſon to be wounded in your ſouls, and to conſult your ſafety, as theſe in my Text did; <hi>When they heard this, they were prick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to their hearts, and ſaid unto Peter, and to the reſt of the Apoſtles; Men and Brethren, What
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:95422:7"/>ſhall we do?</hi> Now the Caſes are, though not equal, yet alike; in theſe <hi>two generals.</hi>
               <list>
                  <item>1. <hi>In the quality and condition of the Perſons that ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered;</hi> The Servant was like the Maſter, King <hi>Charles</hi> like <hi>Jeſus Chriſt our Lord,</hi> as far as by the Divinity and God-head of our Saviour, who had the Spirit without meaſure, and by the frail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of a meer Man there could be a likeneſs.</item>
                  <item>2. <hi>There is a great deal of likeneſs in the guilt that the</hi> Engliſh <hi>have contracted by this Murder, and the</hi> Jews <hi>by the Murder of Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. As for the <hi>Firſt:</hi> the likeneſs between the Perſons, it conſiſteth in theſe particulars;
<list>
                  <item>1. <hi>In their Birth-rights.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>In their <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nction or anoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. <hi>In the Innocency of their lives in ſome proportion.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>4. <hi>In their Patient Deaths.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>5. <hi>In the Indignities that they ſuffered.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>6. <hi>In the likeneſs of the Cauſe;</hi>
                  </item>
               </list> for it was in Both, the cauſe of <hi>Religion,</hi> and for <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi>-ſake.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Firſt,</hi> for their Birth-rights, they were Both, <hi>ad Sceptra nati,</hi> both born to Kingdoms; <hi>Chriſt</hi> to the <hi>Kingdom of Judea,</hi> as appears by his <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nealogy, Mat.</hi> 1. ſpringing in a direct Line from the Loins of <hi>David;</hi> and although he did not exerciſe a temporal juriſdiction, becauſe<note n="(k)" place="margin">Gen 49.10</note> 
               <hi>the Scepter was departed from Judah,</hi> and in the hands of <hi>Herod, when Shiloh came;</hi> yet a greater, a ſpiritual Kingdom he exerciſed. <hi>Charles</hi> alſo, deſcended from an ancient Race of <hi>Britiſh Kings</hi> that were the rightful Governors of theſe Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treys. Nay, it is very obſervable, that their Deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, in reſpect of the diſtance from their origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:95422:8"/>was very much alike; from <hi>David</hi> that ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and eſtabliſhed the <hi>Kingdom</hi> of <hi>Iſrael</hi> to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> were juſt <hi>Twenty-Seven</hi> of the Royal Line, and from <hi>Edward the Confeſſor,</hi> that en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>franchiſed and ſetled this <hi>Kingdom, Charls</hi> I. was <hi>the Twenty ſeventh Monarch.</hi> 2. Both were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>augurated by unction or anointing, the one by the outward Oile of Conſecration; the other with the inward <hi>anointing of the Holy Ghoſt.</hi> and becauſe of this anointing the <hi>Scripture</hi> call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s Name on all that are anointed.<note n="(l)" place="margin">Pſ. 105.15.</note> 
               <hi>Ne tangas Chriſtos meos, Touch not my Chriſts, and do my Prophets no harm;</hi> Both were anoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, but <hi>Chriſt</hi> hath in this the Prerogative above all Earthly Princes, that<note n="(m)" place="margin">Heb. 19.</note> 
               <hi>He was anointed with the Oyl of gladneſs above his fellows.</hi> 3. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like they were, though not equal in Innocency, and a vertuous Life. This <hi>Martyr</hi> went cloſe after the <hi>Foot-ſteps of Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> although he could not overtake-him;<note n="(n)" place="margin">Phil. 3.14.</note> 
               <hi>He preſſed toward the Mark of the high Prize of God. Chriſt</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed was Innocency it ſelf, and as righteous as the Law; This righteous Man was as innocent as was compatible with mortality and common frailty. In all his Relations, he was a moſt emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent example; to his <hi>Children,</hi> the moſt <hi>tender Father</hi> in the World; to his <hi>Queen,</hi> the moſt conſtant and <hi>faithful Husband,</hi> in the Earth; to his <hi>Servants,</hi> the moſt <hi>obliging Lord;</hi> to the <hi>Church, a moſt bleſſed and zealous Patron;</hi> to his <hi>People, Pater-Patriae, a Father of his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey.</hi> He was ſo far from <hi>Tyranny,</hi> that he could
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:95422:8"/>not entertain <hi>jealouſie;</hi> ſo far from <hi>ſeverity and harſhneſs,</hi> that <hi>he could not think ill of his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects,</hi> when they dealt never ſo baſely with him; of ſuch <hi>clemency</hi> and <hi>pitty,</hi> that he was ſo far from <hi>puniſhing</hi> thoſe that <hi>hated him,</hi> that he moſt commonly took them into places of parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular favour and truſt, and ſo hoped that his kindneſs and Princely favours ſhould do on them, what other Princes do by ſeverity and puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. But the returns of that ungracious Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, hath taught the World this <hi>Maxim</hi> of <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, that, Pardon of offenders before their repentance, is but an ill guard to a Prince's Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. To God,</hi> he was a moſt devout and ſincere <hi>votary,</hi> a Perſon of an admirable <hi>zeal</hi> and <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in Religion;</hi> to <hi>Men,</hi> a moſt exact pattern of <hi>Juſtice</hi> and <hi>Equity.</hi> A Prince he was, ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary enricht with grace, that temptations ſeemed to aſſault him, to no end but to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feated: Though he had but three <hi>Kingdoms,</hi> he deſerved <hi>four Crowns;</hi> but the moſt ſplendid of all, for his abſolute Empire over himſelf: for, <hi>ſelf-denyal</hi> which is the task of all other Men, and the moſt harſh Diſcipline in the School of Chriſt, ſeemed to him but <hi>recreation:</hi> He was Snow in the midd'ſt of Flames, and Fire in a Maſs of Ice; He was ſober in the middeſt of <hi>Youth,</hi> when all others are <hi>looſe</hi> and <hi>wild; Spot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs</hi> in deſpight of <hi>Sanguin;</hi> he was <hi>humble</hi> in the <hi>glories</hi> of a <hi>Court,</hi> which uſually make o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers giddy and vain; <hi>abſtinent</hi> in the middeſt of <hi>Feaſts</hi> where <hi>Luxuries</hi> have their dominion,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:95422:9"/>
               <hi>chaſt</hi> in his very <hi>embraces:</hi> He reconciled the <hi>ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of the Croſs,</hi> to the <hi>ſplendor</hi> of <hi>Crowns;</hi> the <hi>Grandeur</hi> of <hi>Purples</hi> to the <hi>ſeverity of Jeſus,</hi> the <hi>glories</hi> of <hi>Kings,</hi> and the <hi>mortification</hi> of a Chriſtian together; and continued a <hi>zealous pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant</hi> in the <hi>Court of Spain</hi> it ſelf. 4. He i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitated <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> in the patience of his death: That he could ſo diſcernably fore-ſee his ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching Fate, did evince him a Perſon of no narrow or common apprehenſion; they are his own words;<note n="(o)" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Medit. 28.</note> 
               <hi>I know that there are but few steps between the Priſons and Graves of Princes.</hi> Yet even then,<note n="(p)" place="margin">Luk 21.19.</note> 
               <hi>With what patience did he poſſeſs his Soul?</hi> With what a great temper and calmneſs of Spirit did he fit himſelf for his end? To which, when by ſad ſtages he ſtill drew neerer, and neerer; by ſerious and frequent Prayers, and by eating the Paſſe-over, by communicating the Lord's Supper in imitation of <hi>Chriſt</hi> his great Pattern, he diſpoſed himſelf to his end; and when it came, drank the Cup without murmur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or repining: He forgave all; prayed for his Enemies; kiſſed the rod, and<note n="(q)" place="margin">Eſa. 53.7.</note> 
               <hi>as a ſheep be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Shearers, he opened not his mouth,</hi> or if he opened his Lips, it was like the opening of the Gates of the Temple, nothing but odors and perfume, nothing but Light and Love, nothing but holy and Chriſtian counſels and bleſſings came from thence. 5. Alike they were in the barbarous indignities that were offered to them; they both, ſuffered the ſcoffs and taunts of wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Men; both,<note n="(r)" place="margin">Heb. 12.3.</note> 
               <hi>endured the contradiction of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners;
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:95422:9"/>Chriſt</hi> from his own <hi>Creatures,</hi> and <hi>Charles</hi> from his own <hi>Subjects; Chriſt Jeſus</hi> ſuffered by the <hi>inſolence</hi> of the <hi>Jews,</hi> and <hi>Charles</hi> by the <hi>inſolence</hi> of the <hi>Engliſh; Chriſt</hi> was charged as a <hi>Traytor to the State,</hi> and ſo was <hi>Charles</hi> too, even by thoſe very Men, who if they had had no other crime, were themſelves <hi>Traytors</hi> in the higheſt degree for that very Fact; <hi>Chriſt</hi> had obliged His Perſecutors, and <hi>Charles</hi> had obliged his: and yet, <hi>Chriſt</hi> was put to Death on a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of<note n="(s)" place="margin">Jo. 18.14.</note> 
               <hi>ſaving the Nation,</hi> to whom His Blood became an <hi>utter ruine;</hi> and on the ſame <hi>pretence,</hi> was <hi>Charles murdered</hi> too; <hi>Sed Deus avertat omen.</hi> 6. They were alike in the cauſe of their Death, both for Religion and for righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs ſake. <hi>Chriſt</hi> dyed to <hi>fownd</hi> and to <hi>ſave</hi> his <hi>Church, Charles,</hi> becauſe he would not <hi>betray</hi> it; <hi>Chriſt</hi> to <hi>ſave</hi> all the World from <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal ſlavery, Charles</hi> to deliver the <hi>Kingdoms</hi> from <hi>illegal Tyranny;</hi> one from the dominion of the <hi>Devil,</hi> and the other from the power of <hi>deviliſh Men:</hi> And it is certain, if he would have yielded to the <hi>ſubverſion</hi> of the <hi>Laws,</hi> the <hi>ruine</hi> of his <hi>Subjects,</hi> and the overthrow of the <hi>Church,</hi> he needed not to have <hi>dyed:</hi> On theſe tearms,<note n="(t)" place="margin">Heb. 11.35, 38.</note> 
               <hi>He would not accept deliverance, nor was the World worthy of him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Again <hi>ſecondly:</hi> The ways by which the Men of this Kingdom, have contracted the guilt of the blood of this pious Prince, are much of the ſame nature, and manner, with thoſe ways by which the <hi>Jews</hi> have contracted the guilt of the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:95422:10"/>blood of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> which will be very diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernable, if we inquire, what the Guilt of the <hi>Jews</hi> was.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>Some Jews contracted the guilt, by direct perſecuting, apprehending, condemning, ſenten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing, and executing of Chriſt.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. <hi>Some contracted the guilt of his Blood, by proſecuting of him, and ſoliciting his Death.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3. <hi>Some by conſenting to it, and delighting in it.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>4. <hi>All of them by two ways.</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. <hi>By not hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering of it as much as they were able.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. <hi>By being lyable to the Acts and Conſultations of their Repreſentatives and Proxies in thoſe great Counſels.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. Some by direct perſecution, apprehenſion, condemnation, ſentence, and execution. Thus were the <hi>High-Prieſt,</hi> and <hi>Sanhedrim,</hi> guilty, when they combined againſt him, <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.3. <hi>The chief Prieſts, and the Rulers, and the Elders of the People conſpired againſt him, to take him by ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilty, and to kill him.</hi> They reſolved to put him to Death, before they apprehended him; But becauſe they would <hi>delude</hi> the <hi>vulgar,</hi> and not be thought to do any thing <hi>unjuſtly,</hi> after <hi>Cai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aphas</hi> had examined him, he calls for the <hi>ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frages</hi> of the <hi>Councel,</hi> verſ. 66. <hi>What think ye? And they ſaid, He is guilty of Death.</hi> Thus theſe were guilty of his blood by <hi>condemning</hi> of him; <hi>Judas</hi> by <hi>betraying</hi> him; <hi>Pilate</hi> was guilty by <hi>ſentencing</hi> of him; and others guilty by <hi>execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting</hi> of him.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:95422:10"/>
            <p n="2">2. Some became guilty of Chriſt's blood by <hi>ſoliciting</hi> of his death, when<note n="(u)" place="margin">Mat. 27 22, 22.</note> 
               <hi>Pontius Pilate</hi> asked the Multitude, what he ſhould do with <hi>Jeſus,</hi> their anſwer was, <hi>Let Him be crucified, let Him be crucified;</hi> And when he (according to that ceremony uſual in the Law) <hi>had waſhed his hands,</hi> thereby (as he thought) acquitting his conſcience; they take all the <hi>guilt</hi> of it on <hi>themſelves</hi> and their <hi>poſterities;</hi>
               <note n="(x)" place="margin">Verſ. 25.</note> 
               <hi>Let his blood be upon us, and our children for ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Some became guilty of the blood of Chriſt by <hi>conſenting</hi> to it, and that either, <hi>à priori,</hi> or <hi>à poſteriori:</hi> Either 1. before the fact, by approving the proceedings, by being pleaſed with the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, or execution; As<note n="(a)" place="margin">Acts 22.20.</note> St. <hi>Paul</hi> became guilty of the murder of St. <hi>Stephen by holding the Garments of thoſe that stoned him.</hi> 2. Some became guilty of his death, <hi>ex poſt-facto,</hi> by ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king content in the thing done; by being ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to the good way that he preached and dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to build up. <hi>Saul</hi> was a Perſecuter of him after his death, becauſe he was about to appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> and hinder his word. <hi>Saul, Saul, why perſecuteſt thou me? Act.</hi> 9.4.</p>
            <p n="4">4. All the <hi>Jews</hi> were guilty of this Murder by theſe two ways.
<list>
                  <item>1. <hi>Becauſe they did not</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">Voluntas eſt cauſe peccati per accidens, non impediendo, vel non repri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendo cum poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit. <hi>Aq. Sum. 22&amp;.</hi> q. <hi>15 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>. 5.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der this horrible Murder as much as they were able.</hi> Juſtice and righteouſneſs doth exact, that according to our power, <hi>we defend the innocent, and plead the cauſe of the oppreſſed,</hi> whereas they tamely connived at the burden of that im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pious
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:95422:11"/>ſentence,<note place="margin">Qui non vetat peceare cum poſſit, jubet.</note> although he ſpake as never man ſpake, and did Miracles in their ſight, which none but <hi>God</hi> could do.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>2dly.</hi> But however, <hi>they were guilty in the very Fact and condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Sanhedrim or great Council,</hi> becauſe it was a Council <hi>delegated</hi> by <hi>themſelves,</hi>
                     <note n="†" place="margin">Franc. Jun. Analytic. expoſ. Num. <hi>12.</hi>
                     </note> cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen out of their <hi>Tribes, Six out of a Tribe, by the Elections and Voices of the People.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list> And truly, ſince thoſe <hi>Tribes</hi> made no more conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence what <hi>kind</hi> of <hi>Perſons</hi> they did <hi>elect,</hi> it was moſt <hi>equitable</hi> that the <hi>guilt</hi> which their <hi>repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentatives</hi> had contracted, ſhould fall on the whole Nation. And theſe I apprehend to be the principal cauſes and reaſons, why, when the <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle</hi> chargeth <hi>Chriſt's murder</hi> ſo directly, ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terminately on the <hi>Jews,</hi> the whole Multitude of the <hi>Jews</hi> promiſcuouſly: there is not any that openeth his Mouth againſt it; there is not one Perſon that doth at all object; there is no Man that doth deny, or that doth attempt ſo much as to excuſe, or extenuate the Fact; but they ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge it to be a great and a fearful truth; the remembrance of it is bitter unto them; and they conſult their ſafety, and the expiation of it, <hi>When they heard this, they were pricked to their hearts, and ſaid unto</hi> Peter, <hi>and to the reſt of the Apoſtles, Men and Brethren, What ſhall we do?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Truly the ſame ſeveral ways, and many more are the <hi>Engliſh</hi> guilty of the <hi>Blood</hi> of this <hi>Incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable Prince.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Some, By direct and point-blank-fighting
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:95422:11"/>againſt him, to conquer him, to kill him, to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſon, to implead, condemn, ſentence, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecute him; and thus were all thoſe guilty of his blood, that ever lifted up their hands or tongues againſt him; thus was every Man guilty, that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver drew a Sword in that cauſe or quarrel a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him; the queſtion of the Prophet <hi>David</hi> is impoſſible to be eluded.<note n="(b)" place="margin">1 Sam. 26 9</note> 
               <hi>Can any Man lift up his hand againſt the Lords anointed, and be guiltleſs?</hi> that is, No Man can ever lift up his hand againſt the Lord's anointed, and be guiltleſs. And therefore ſuch have no way to reconcile themſelves to God for it, but by a real and perpetual Sorrow, and Repentance, as long as they live, and by the ſatisfaction of <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s blood; But eſpecially thoſe bloody and barbarous <hi>Regicides</hi> that ſate as <hi>Co-Aſſeſsors</hi> at his <hi>condemnation,</hi> or as <hi>Aſſiſtants</hi> at his <hi>Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Some contracted the guilt of his blood by <hi>ſoliciting</hi> his death, and thus did the blind and ignorant Rabble, by the <hi>inſtigation</hi> of the <hi>prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal Rebels</hi> and <hi>Incendiaries, petition</hi> and <hi>cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour</hi> for his <hi>blood,</hi> under the ſpecious Name of <hi>Juſtice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Some of you were guilty by <hi>conſenting</hi> to this horrible Fact, and that either <hi>à priori,</hi> while your thoughts took any pleaſure in the practice of this execrable deed, whatever temptations you had to deſire it. And ſome of you, <hi>ex poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>facto,</hi> when you took any ſatisfaction in the thing done; while you <hi>apoſtatized</hi> from your
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:95422:12"/>own <hi>reaſon</hi> and <hi>principles,</hi> and <hi>aſſociated</hi> your ſelves to thoſe <hi>Regicides,</hi> while you became <hi>vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntary aſſiſtants</hi> to <hi>execute</hi> their <hi>commands,</hi> or any way inſtrumental to help them defend that intereſt that they had graſped unto themſelves, by the <hi>Murder</hi> of this <hi>Holy Man</hi> out of any baſe <hi>Fears,</hi> or greedy <hi>Hopes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. All were guilty of this blood, that did not, as much as they could, hinder the effuſion of it, while they looked on it with an indifferent eye; while they ſate ſtill at their caſe, without endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring to prevent, or reverſe that curſed ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence. For I muſt tell you, that that <hi>Maxim</hi> of <hi>Self-preſervation,</hi> when the <hi>life</hi> of our <hi>Prince</hi> is at <hi>stake,</hi> is but a <hi>meer Sophiſm,</hi> in the <hi>School</hi> of <hi>Chriſt.</hi> He that preferrs any Member to the Head, muſt needs be very unskilful in the neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities of a Natural Body; and he that preferrs his own condition, before the condition of his <hi>Prince,</hi> is altogether an <hi>unprofitable Member</hi> of the <hi>body politique,</hi> and falls below the <hi>faith</hi> and <hi>loyalty</hi> of the very <hi>Infidels</hi> themſelves. And I appeal to your own experience, whether <hi>Thoſe that are ſo much Gods to themſelves, are, not Devils to all others.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>However, remember that the <hi>grand Factors</hi> in this <hi>bloody buſineſs,</hi> were your <hi>Delegates;</hi> that they did act at all, was by your Elections and choice; The <hi>conſciences</hi> of thoſe Men were ſuch as you did <hi>approve</hi> of, or elſe they would never have been choſen into that <hi>great Councel</hi> of the Kingdom by your <hi>Votes;</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Peccatum con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingit in ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quem Dupliciter vel in ſe qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ad actum peccati; vel in ſua cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa. <hi>Aq. Sum. 22ae. q. 154.5.0.</hi>
               </note> ſo that their <hi>Acts</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:95422:12"/>
               <hi>your own.</hi> And if you had not <hi>wilfully reſolved</hi> to have had ſuch <hi>counſels</hi> and <hi>events;</hi> Why did you <hi>chooſe</hi> Perſons of ſo <hi>deſperate</hi> and <hi>deſtructive Principles;</hi> ſome of them being ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally known, and ſome of them <hi>stigmatized,</hi> for <hi>turbulent</hi> and <hi>factious Perſons,</hi> Men that were <hi>Enemies</hi> to <hi>peace</hi> and <hi>order.</hi> Theſe were your <hi>Patriots;</hi> and you ſee, into what condition their <hi>Counſels</hi> and <hi>Acts</hi> brought you to. Nor is it to be wondered at. For who ever knew the <hi>Soul</hi> taken away, and the <hi>Body</hi> not ſuffer <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vulſions?</hi> So that there remains no more excuſe for you, than for the <hi>Jews;</hi> nor are you any more able to <hi>deny</hi> or <hi>extenuate</hi> the <hi>Fact,</hi> than the <hi>Jews</hi> could <hi>deny, excuſe</hi> or <hi>extenuate,</hi> the <hi>Murder</hi> of <hi>Chriſt.</hi> Nay farther; even thoſe Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons that thought that they had <hi>defended</hi> this <hi>Prince,</hi> have too much of the <hi>guilt</hi> and <hi>stain</hi> of his <hi>Blood</hi> on their Garments and <hi>Souls,</hi> as I ſhall make appear Anon.</p>
            <p>In the mean time, let us conſider what this Sin of Murder is. A Crime it is of ſo heynous a nature, that if it were but caſually and acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentally committed, it was death by the <hi>Judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial Law,</hi> if the criminal were taken before he came to the <hi>City of Refuge.</hi> Num. 35. But if <hi>wilful</hi> and <hi>preſumptuous,</hi> he muſt dye, though he came thither. <hi>Exod.</hi> 21.12. <hi>Thou ſhalt take him away from mine Altar, that he may dye.</hi> The <hi>Altar</hi> it ſelf ſhall not <hi>protect</hi> him. Nor did the guilt of Blood extend only to Perſons; But it polluted the <hi>Land,</hi> Num. 35.33. Although it
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:95422:13"/>were <hi>involuntarily ſpilt:</hi> But, for the <hi>wilful Murder,</hi> no expiation admitted. <hi>The Land mourns for ſuch, and therefore thine Eye ſhall not pitty him, that it may go well with thee, when thou ſhalt have put away from Iſrael the guilt of Innocent Blood.</hi> Deut. 19.11, 12, 13. The <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> pronounceth an heavy ſentence on ſuch Offenders. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 55.23. <hi>The bloody and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitful Man ſhall not live out half his Days;</hi> or if he do live longer, better it were for him that he did not: for he doth but accumulate and heap up, as well as protract vengeance; he doth but<note n="(c)" place="margin">Rom. 2.5.</note> 
               <hi>treaſure up wrath, againſt the Day of Wrath,</hi> and increaſe his fearful account, till that time ſurprize him, wherein the moſt righteous and impartial Judge ſhall <hi>come in Flames of Fire to make Inquiſition for Blood.</hi> God conſulted and took deliberation, when he made Man, <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.26. <hi>Let us make Man after our own Image, after our likeneſs;</hi> And he takes deliberation likewiſe in ſending Judgments to deſtroy Man; as he extinguiſhed the <hi>Canaanites</hi> by little and little.<note n="(d)" place="margin">Pſal. 103.14.</note> 
               <hi>He knows whereof we are made, he remembers that we are but duſt;</hi> and yet he is a Lord of a moſt infinite and an abſolute power; and ſurely, it is very unreaſonable for the choi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt buildings to be caſt into rude hands to be demoliſhed; he is moſt skilful to pull down that raiſed the Fabrick, and to him it is moſt reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to be committed. A Sin directly againſt the command of God; a command in force in all Ages, a <hi>command,</hi> againſt which there ſhall
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:95422:13"/>never be a <hi>counter-mand.</hi> Before the <hi>Moral Law: He that ſheds Man's blood, by Man ſhall his blood be ſhed,</hi> Gen. 9.6. Repeated at Mount <hi>Sinah. Thou ſhalt do no Murder,</hi> Exod. 20. No Murder of any ſort, or any degree. Expounded moſt <hi>strictly</hi> by <hi>Chriſt.</hi> Thou ſhalt do nothing that may tend to murder;<note n="(e)" place="margin">Mat. 5.22.</note> 
               <hi>Thou ſhalt not be angry without a cauſe;</hi> Thou ſhalt be ſo far from killing <hi>deliberately,</hi> that thou ſhalt not do it <hi>raſhly;</hi> nay, thou ſhalt be ſo far from doing of it <hi>raſhly,</hi> that thou ſhalt not begin the leaſt <hi>heat,</hi> that may tend to ſo bad an end. A ſin it is, clamorous to Heaven for vengeance; ſo doth the <hi>first blood</hi> from the <hi>Earth, Gen.</hi> 4.10. And ſo do the <hi>Souls</hi> from under the <hi>Altar,</hi> Rev. 6.10. <hi>And they cryed with a loud voice, ſaying, How long, O God, holy, and true, doſt thou not judge, and avenge our blood on them that dwell on the Earth?</hi> But to ſum up all the evil that can be thought of, or ſpoken againſt this ſin, I ſhall need do no more, than add the <hi>commentary</hi> of the <hi>beloved Diſciple,</hi> St. <hi>John,</hi> on that <hi>Command.</hi> 1 Jo. 3.15. <hi>You know that no Murderer hath E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Life abiding in him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But this Wickedneſs that we now treat of, was the moſt <hi>horrible Murder</hi> that ever was <hi>committed.</hi> A raſing of <hi>Adam</hi>'s <hi>Image,</hi> and <hi>God</hi>'s too. A <hi>parricide,</hi> a killing of our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. A <hi>Regicide,</hi> a Murdering of our <hi>Prince;</hi> a violation of all bonds of <hi>Honour, Faith,</hi> and <hi>Allegiance;</hi> a deſperate and wilful <hi>Perjury,</hi> and
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:95422:14"/>breach of your <hi>Oaths</hi> of <hi>Fealty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> You'l ſay, Alas! It was far beſides mine intent, that ever ſo vile and curſed a thing as this is, ſhould have come to paſs; ſo that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though I were a <hi>caſual,</hi> I was not an <hi>intentional Inſtrument;</hi> Although I was an <hi>acceſſary,</hi> I was far from being a <hi>principal</hi> in this heavy Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gedy.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Be not miſtaken, this is no excuſe at all; For in <hi>caſe of Treaſon,</hi> there is no <hi>Law</hi> in the World that accounts any Agent an <hi>Acceſſary</hi> only; they are all <hi>Principals.</hi> Nor was ever any thing in the Earth heard of, that in every cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance had more of baſeneſs, than this Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der: For <hi>firſt,</hi> it was <hi>leiſurely</hi> and <hi>deliberately plotted</hi> and <hi>contrived,</hi> and ſo could not have the excuſe of <hi>heat</hi> or <hi>paſſion:</hi> It was acted againſt the moſt <hi>known</hi> and <hi>publick Perſon</hi> of the <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> and ſo could not have the excuſe of <hi>igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance:</hi> It was done in the moſt <hi>open</hi> and <hi>impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent manner, in the ſight of this Sun;</hi> and ſo could not have the ſhelter of <hi>modeſty</hi> and <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealment:</hi> It was acted againſt our <hi>King,</hi> and our <hi>Governor,</hi> and ſo could not have any excuſe from <hi>ſub ordination</hi> or <hi>co-ordination;</hi> For, <hi>The King is Supream,</hi> 1 Pet. 2.13. And then it will naturally follow, than none can queſtion him: Job 34.18. <hi>Who can ſay to a King, thou art wicked? and to Princes, ye are ungodly?</hi> It was done upon our <hi>Governor</hi> and our <hi>Maſter:</hi> and then remember the queſtion of that Woman,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:95422:14"/>
               <note n="(f)" place="margin">2 Reg 9.31.</note> 
               <hi>Had Zimri peace who ſlew his Maſter?</hi> It was done out of a perfect <hi>effront</hi> and <hi>contempt</hi> of <hi>Religion;</hi> for <hi>the freedom of the Goſpel</hi> was pretended, for that, which was moſt expreſly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it; For you know who hath ſaid,<note n="(g)" place="margin">Rom. 13.1.</note> 
               <hi>Let every Soul be ſubject to the Higher Powers.</hi> Nay it was done under the covert of <hi>God's Ordinance,</hi> and ſo <hi>God's own honour</hi> was <hi>proſtituted</hi> to coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance this <hi>horrible Villany;</hi> his <hi>glory</hi> made to <hi>lacquey</hi>-after the <hi>practices</hi> of <hi>deſperate</hi> and <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natural Rebels;</hi> So that, as the <hi>Caſuiſts</hi> ſay of <hi>Inceſt; If it be committed without marriage it is a great ſin; but greater if under marriage, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe God's holy Inſtitution is made to mask un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanneſs;</hi> ſo ſay I, To have <hi>murdered</hi> our <hi>Prince</hi> was a <hi>tranſcendent</hi> and <hi>horrible impiety;</hi> but, To do it under the <hi>pretext</hi> of <hi>God's Ordinance,</hi> and under the <hi>Formalities</hi> and <hi>Ceremonies</hi> of <hi>Juſtice,</hi> is <hi>intollerable;</hi> It was as much a <hi>mockery</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> as it was an <hi>abuſe</hi> to the <hi>King.</hi> Nay, the <hi>Form</hi> of proceeding was as contrary to all Rules of <hi>Equity,</hi> as <hi>the matter of Fact</hi> was <hi>execrable.</hi> It is an equitable <hi>Maxim</hi> in all <hi>Laws,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Juſtian. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitut.</note> 
               <hi>Ne ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicet pars, Let not a party be the Judge;</hi> and yet, Who were the <hi>Proſecutors,</hi> but his own <hi>Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies,</hi> that were <hi>parties,</hi> and in actual Arms a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him? Who <hi>witneſſes,</hi> but thoſe very <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels</hi> that were <hi>parties</hi> in the quarrel, and whom he attempted to have <hi>chaſtiſed?</hi> Who were his <hi>Judges,</hi> but thoſe very <hi>parties</hi> and <hi>enemies</hi> that had continued a moſt <hi>barbarous War</hi> againſt him?
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:95422:15"/>and when their own Villanies had put them out of all hope of Pardon, they knew not how to ſecure themſelves from the Puniſhment that they had deſerved, but by inflicting an ungodly Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence on Him: <hi>Though he knew how to forgive, they knew not how to truſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To be ſhort, They had no colour of <hi>wrong;</hi> For, by the <hi>Law,</hi>
               <note n="‖" place="margin">
                  <hi>Cook</hi> on <hi>Lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleton.</hi> Lib. 1. Fol. 19.</note> 
               <hi>The King can do no wrong.</hi> They could not urge againſt him, as the <hi>Jews</hi> did againſt <hi>Chriſt, That he was an enemy to Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar;</hi>
               <note n="(h)" place="margin">Jo. 19.12.</note> For here was no other <hi>Caeſar</hi> but himſelf. They could not believe (if he had been a Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, and not a Prince) that their proceedings were <hi>Legal;</hi> For, <hi>it was a way of Tryal,</hi> ſtudied <hi>after the Fact;</hi> ſo that this moſt unheard-of Murder, was a violation of all that was <hi>good, civil, juſt, equitable,</hi> or <hi>ſacred; a breach of faith, honour, law, equity,</hi> and <hi>gratitude;</hi> a <hi>proſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of <hi>religion, juſtice,</hi> and even of <hi>common hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity it ſelf;</hi> So impudent, ſo fowl, ſo bloody, ſo mercileſs, and barbarous it was!</p>
            <p>And now me-thinks, <hi>Brethren;</hi> when any di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs, when any calamity or National Judgment comes on us, our <hi>diſquieted conſciences</hi> ſhould immediately flie in our Faces, and put us in mind of the <hi>condition</hi> of this <hi>unfortunate,</hi> but <hi>excellent Prince;</hi> As the <hi>Brethren of Joſeph</hi> did, in their intricacies and dangers, call to mind the <hi>cries,</hi> and the <hi>blood of their Brother,</hi> Gen. 42.21, 22. For, when that fearful <hi>Famine</hi> fell upon them, ſo that they were forced into <hi>Aegypt</hi> to
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:95422:15"/>keep themſelves and their Families from periſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and, inſtead of finding <hi>proviſion</hi> and <hi>relief,</hi> were all like to be put into <hi>Priſon;</hi> they preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly apprehended this to be, <hi>Nemeſis à tergo, Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance purſuing them at the heels;</hi> and had in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly theſe ſad reflections on their own hearts. <hi>They ſaid one to another, Verily we are guilty concerning our Brother, in that we ſaw the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh of his Soul, and when he beſought us, we would not hear him, therefore is this diſtreſs come upon us; And Reuben anſwered and ſaid, Spake I not unto you, ſaying, Do not this ſin a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Child? and ye would not hear, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore alſo behold his blood is required.</hi> So had it been moſt reaſonable for you in any of thoſe <hi>National Judgments</hi> that have of late Years worn out the <hi>strength</hi> and <hi>glory</hi> of this Nation, to have caſt your Eyes on this <hi>Bloody Fact.</hi> When that fearful and devouring Plague caſt down all before it; How moſt juſt had it been for you to have accuſed your ſelves, and ſaid, <hi>We are ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily guilty concerning that moſt pious Prince, in that we ſaw the moſt barbarous indignities, and the baſe uſages that were offered unto him, and we either aſſiſted in the Tragedy, or stirred not to prevent it.</hi> When that Foreign <hi>War</hi> ſo much baffled and defeated the Force of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom; How natural had the Inference been? <hi>Now is the Blood of CHARLES required of us, and therefore doth vengeance purſue us.</hi> Or when that fearful <hi>Fire</hi> had waſted and conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:95422:16"/>the <hi>Capital City,</hi> and made it a confuſed Heap of Rubbiſh and Stones; How proper had it been for us, and them, to have ſaid, <hi>Was not the Anointed of the Lord taken in our ſnares? and how juſt is it, that when we made no con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience to extinguiſh</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">2 Sam. 21.17.</note> 
               <hi>the light of Iſrael, we our ſelves ſhould be extinguiſhed.</hi> And the <hi>Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers of the Lord,</hi> from this place (as they have done heretofore) have juſt reaſon to urge againſt you, as <hi>Reuben</hi> did; <hi>Spake we not unto you, ſaying, Do not this ſin againſt the Lord's A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed, and against this pious Father of this Church and Kingdom: but ye would not hear; therefore behold his Blood is required of you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But becauſe there is in Men different <hi>degrees</hi> of <hi>guilt,</hi> according, as ſome have been <hi>Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental</hi> and <hi>Active</hi> in this <hi>Murder;</hi> as ſome have been <hi>conſenting</hi> to it; as ſome have been <hi>neu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tral, cold,</hi> and <hi>aſleep;</hi> when it might have been <hi>prevented:</hi> I had need accordingly to apply my ſelf ſeverally unto them; and I ſhall hope that God's Holy Spirit will ſo inforce it on all your conſciences, that no Man may depart hence with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a <hi>wounded</hi> and a <hi>ſad heart,</hi> no <hi>Face</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>paleneſs,</hi> no <hi>Eye</hi> without a <hi>tear,</hi> which is moſt proper and ſuitable to the <hi>Solemnity</hi> of this <hi>black</hi> and <hi>ſad Day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But <hi>first,</hi> For thoſe that rebelliouſly <hi>unſhea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed the Sword,</hi> pretending to plead the <hi>cauſe of God,</hi> againſt <hi>GOD's Vice-Roy;</hi> Let me per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade you to think ſeriouſly with your ſelves,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:95422:16"/>
               <hi>Who thoſe are,</hi> to whom God hath <hi>ſhared</hi> his <hi>Name,</hi> where he gives this <hi>character</hi> of them, <hi>I have ſaid ye are Gods, and all of you Children of the most higheſt,</hi> Pſal. 82.6. And withall, do but imagine with your ſelves, what kind of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons thoſe are, that the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> deſcribes, <hi>Jude</hi> Verſ. 8.11. <hi>that deſpiſe dominion, that ſpeak evil of dignities, that walk in the way of Cain,</hi> the firſt Murderer; <hi>and periſh in the gain-ſaying of Corah,</hi> the moſt obſtinate Rebel in the World; and bewail your condition. O remember how many ſad <hi>Widdows curſes,</hi> how many <hi>Orphans tears</hi> your <hi>Swords</hi> have drawn on your <hi>Heads,</hi> and how many <hi>ruined Families groans</hi> attended your <hi>ſucceſſes.</hi> Remember the <hi>Blood</hi> of your <hi>Fellow-ſubjects,</hi> that were <hi>Defenders</hi> of the <hi>Laws,</hi> and ſo more righteous than your ſelves,<note n="(i)" place="margin">1 Reg. 2.5.</note> 
               <hi>That, you put on the Girdles that were on your Loins, and into the Shoos that were on your Feet;</hi> and be ſure of this,<note n="(k)" place="margin">Iam. 5.2, 3, 4.</note> 
               <hi>That the Gold and the Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver that you have gathered, by ſuch violence, and deſperate courſes, ſhall contract a ruſt, and canker, that ſhall be a witneſs againſt you, and ſhall eat out your Fleſh, as it were Fire; you have heaped treaſure together for the laſt Days, and that which you have gathered doth cry, and hath entered into the Ears of the Lord of Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baoth; and</hi>
               <note n="(l)" place="margin">Mat. 23 32.</note> 
               <hi>to fill up the meaſure of your ſins always, you have at laſt mercileſly and cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elly cut off the Lord's Anointed, of whom we ſaid, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder his ſhadow ſhall we rejoyce.</hi> Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:95422:17"/>you ſhould now hear the dreadful Alarum of that laſt <hi>Trumpet,</hi> and that fearful <hi>Voice</hi> of the <hi>Arch-Angel; Ariſe ye dead and come to Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment:</hi> Suppoſe you ſhould now ſee this <hi>glorious</hi> and <hi>beatified Prince</hi> coming amidſt the <hi>Army of Martyrs,</hi> with his <hi>Lord Chriſt</hi> to Judge the World; and that he ſhould ſhew unto you his <hi>Blood,</hi> that you regardleſly ſpilt, <hi>like Water on the ground:</hi> What have you to plead for your ſelves before the righteous Judge? <hi>The Act of Indemnity?</hi> Alas, that is a very poor means to waſh away the ſtains of Blood; there is great difference betwixt <hi>Reaſon of State,</hi> and the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings of the <hi>Supream Judge;</hi> that which can quiet a <hi>Kingdom,</hi> is far enough from <hi>calming</hi> and quieting your <hi>Conſciences;</hi> It can be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but your <hi>strict</hi> and <hi>unfeigned Repentance,</hi> that can gain you the pardon of this Sin. But I tremble to think how far, generally, this kind of Sinners are from this grace, which only can expiate their Guilt; it grieves me to remember how few there are, that when they have once come to this impudent heighth, <hi>have ever been renewed again by repentance.</hi> Which is very evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, if you'l call to mind theſe <hi>two remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able things.</hi> The <hi>firſt</hi> is this: How many have we known that have been reputed <hi>enemies,</hi> and <hi>perſecuted,</hi> and <hi>undone</hi> for <hi>preaching</hi> this <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine</hi> of <hi>Repentance</hi> to them? So far from re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penting of their Wickedneſs, that they were ready to Murder any Perſon <hi>that ſhould tell them
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:95422:17"/>the truth.</hi> The ſecond is this: How few were there of the Members of that <hi>Abaddon,</hi> that when they came to <hi>publick infamous ends</hi> for this <hi>Murder,</hi> that ever repented them of this deed. So that we may conclude, that <hi>Rebellion is indeed as the ſin of Witchcraft;</hi>
               <note n="(m)" place="margin">1 Sam. 15.23.</note> as <hi>impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent,</hi> and as <hi>unnatural;</hi> as hateful to <hi>God,</hi> and as far from <hi>Repentance;</hi> and truly we may then expect a great number of <hi>penitent Witches,</hi> when we hear of <hi>penitent Regicides.</hi> But the <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>God</hi> can do the <hi>Miracles</hi> that we <hi>cannot think,</hi> and therefore to him we commit this great work. <hi>Do thou, O God, break the Rocks of their hearts, and make them truly ſenſible, how difficult it is to obtain the pardon of ſo great a Sin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for you that have <hi>conſented</hi> before, or af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards to this <hi>bloody Fact,</hi> Deal faithfully with your own Souls; make not leſs of it, than indeed it is;<note n="(n)" place="margin">1 Cor. 11.31.</note> 
               <hi>Judge your ſelves, and ye ſhall not be judged, condemn your ſelves, and ye ſhall not be condemned;</hi> make your peace with God before<note n="(o)" place="margin">Amos 6.3.</note> 
               <hi>the evil Day comes;</hi> Leave not this <hi>Guilt</hi> on your <hi>Houſes,</hi> nor this <hi>Pollution, like the Leproſie of Gehazi,</hi> on your Poſterities for ever; Do you <hi>lament</hi> and <hi>deplore</hi> the <hi>deed,</hi> and teach your Children to <hi>abominate</hi> the <hi>practice;</hi> make them to underſtand the <hi>nature,</hi> and the <hi>experienced conſequents</hi> of <hi>Rebellion;</hi> And let us all <hi>bewail</hi> this <hi>Murder,</hi> and ſupplicate God's pardon for it.<note n="(p)" place="margin">Joel 2.15, 16, 17.</note> 
               <hi>Gather the People, ſanctifie the Congregation; Aſſemble the Elders, gather
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:95422:18"/>the Children, and thoſe that ſuck the Breaſts, let the Bridegroom go out of his Chamber, and the Bride out of her Cloſet; Let the Prieſts, the Miniſters of the Lord weep between the Porch and the Altar, and let them ſay, Spare thy People O Lord, and give not thine Heritage to reproach; Wherefore ſhould they ſay among the Heathen, where is now their God?</hi> As for you that were <hi>Neuters,</hi> take ſhame to your Faces, that you could ſit <hi>quiet Spectators</hi> of this <hi>Bloody Tragedy,</hi> and never lift up your hands to divert the Blow. It was the brave Spirit of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>riah in</hi>
               <note n="(q)" place="margin">2 Sam 11.11.</note> 
               <hi>Samuel: The Ark, and Iſrael abide in Tents, and my Lord Joab, and the Servants of my Lord are incam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped in the open Fields, Shall I then go into mine Houſe to eat, and to drink, and to lye with my Wife? as thou liveſt, and as thy Soul liveth, I will not do this thing.</hi> Do you think that this was done like the <hi>Children</hi> of <hi>the true old vali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant Britains,</hi> to let your <hi>courage,</hi> and <hi>honour, like neglected Swords ruſt in your Cells,</hi> and let the <hi>Enemy deſtroy</hi> your <hi>Father</hi> and your <hi>Prince?</hi> And what <hi>gained</hi> you by this <hi>indifferency?</hi> you were afterwards ſeverely <hi>chaſtiſed</hi> for your <hi>ſleep;</hi> and <hi>experience,</hi> hath now taught you, that in <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolent Rebellions,</hi> there is as little <hi>ſecurity</hi> for the <hi>Neuter,</hi> as for him that is the moſt <hi>vigorous Defender of the Laws;</hi> and whatſoever his <hi>fate</hi> is, be ſure none will take <hi>pity</hi> on any ſuch.</p>
            <p>But ſeeing <hi>that Repentance</hi> is very defective in thoſe, where paſt evils give not counſel of fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture care, and conſcience, ſince nothing can <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deem</hi>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:95422:18"/>our <hi>credit</hi> in that which is <hi>paſt,</hi> but our <hi>prudence</hi> and better <hi>management</hi> in the <hi>time to come:</hi> Give me leave to adviſe all <hi>true</hi> and <hi>loyal Engliſh-men,</hi> as one that ſhall in ſome meaſure ſhare in your Proſperity, or in your Smart, to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low thoſe things that tend to the <hi>quiet</hi> of your own <hi>hearts,</hi> and that make for the <hi>peace,</hi> and <hi>glory of God's Church</hi> amongſt us, and the <hi>hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs</hi> of our <hi>dear</hi> and <hi>Native-Countrey.</hi> And now you ſee the <hi>Rock,</hi> where you have once al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready <hi>ſuffered Shipwrack,</hi> be ſure to avoid it. Particularly, take care <hi>that you become not guilty of</hi>
               <note n="(r)" place="margin">As the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle adviſer others in a caſe not much unlike, <hi>1</hi> Tim. <hi>5.22.</hi> Et ubi cadem ratio, idem jus.</note> 
               <hi>other Mens ſins,</hi> by putting Perſons of <hi>dangerous Principles</hi> in a <hi>capacity</hi> of doing <hi>pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick miſchief. Remember the Blood of CHARLS the Firſt,</hi> and whoſe <hi>Delegates</hi> they were that brought his <hi>Blood on all your Heads.</hi> Know that at the laſt Day, when <hi>God</hi> ſhall Judge all the deeds of Men, all your <hi>priviledges,</hi> and your <hi>capacities,</hi> and <hi>elections</hi> muſt be accounted for; and therefore ſee that you uſe <hi>unbyaſſed,</hi> and <hi>cleer Conſciences</hi> in giving <hi>your ſuffrages,</hi> to thoſe that are to have hand in the <hi>Legiſlative Councels</hi> of this <hi>great Kingdom.</hi> Let there be no<note n="(s)" place="margin">2 Sam. 16.7, 8.</note> 
               <hi>Shimei's to ſpeak evil of Rulers;</hi> no<note n="(t)" place="margin">Gen 9.22.</note> curſed <hi>Cham's to pry into their Fathers naked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs;</hi> no <hi>mutinous, ſullen,</hi> and <hi>unpeaceable ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits;</hi> Let there be no Men of <hi>inſolent</hi> and <hi>am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitious tempers;</hi> Let there be none that are <hi>gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy</hi> of <hi>innovations;</hi> None that have an <hi>itch</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>ways unknown to the Laws,</hi> under which <hi>your Fathers have for many Years flouriſhed;</hi>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:95422:19"/>Let them be <hi>true old zealous Proteſtants,</hi> that<note n="(u)" place="margin">1 Pet. 2.17</note> love their <hi>neighbours,</hi> that <hi>fear God, and honor the King.</hi> Then<note n="(x)" place="margin">Exo. 20.12</note> 
               <hi>You may live long in the Land, which the Lord your GOD hath given you,</hi>
               <note n="(y)" place="margin">Pſ. 112.17</note> 
               <hi>to ſee your Childrens Children, and peace upon Iſrael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But by the way, ſee that you all perfectly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the <hi>poyſon</hi> and <hi>miſchief</hi> of that one <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſtian practice,</hi> of <hi>Dethroning Princes,</hi> and<note n="(a)" place="margin">2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.4.</note> 
               <hi>of Mens exalting themſelves above all that is called God;</hi> and let this never be forgotten, that whether this be practiſed by the <hi>Tyranny and Pride of One,</hi> or <hi>Many;</hi> whether by the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation</hi> of the <hi>Pope,</hi> or by the <hi>Madneſs</hi> of <hi>Secta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries;</hi> 'tis juſtifiable in both alike; that is, it is in either, a <hi>Character</hi> of <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> and a <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Devils.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to conclude, becauſe it is utterly unfit, that in a thing of this ſerious, and <hi>lamentable nature</hi> and <hi>importance,</hi> I ſhould deal <hi>partially,</hi> and forbear any Perſons, that by any means, lye un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the <hi>Guilt</hi> of this <hi>Crying Blood,</hi> and eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, now my promiſe hath obliged me to ſpare none; I muſt be bold to affirm that which yet is a very ſad thing to relate, that too many of thoſe, that have caſt the whole charge of the <hi>Guilt</hi> of this <hi>Blood</hi> on the Perſons of <hi>others,</hi> are <hi>themſelves</hi> in a great meaſure <hi>Guilty</hi> of the <hi>Blood</hi> of this <hi>bleſſed Prince.</hi> Many there were that gained themſelves a <hi>name</hi> and <hi>honor</hi> by adhearing to his Cauſe, that were the greateſt Inſtruments and means of the <hi>miſcarriage</hi> and <hi>unſucceſsful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:95422:19"/>of it. And alas, how many were there that had nothing <hi>good</hi> in them, but the <hi>empty cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter</hi> of <hi>Loyalty,</hi> and under that <hi>skreen</hi> did more <hi>miſchief</hi> than the moſt <hi>incorrigible</hi> and <hi>furious Rebels</hi> of the whole <hi>Kingdom?</hi> Nay, it was im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible, that ever the enemy could have ſtudied ſo many <hi>advantages,</hi> as you your ſelves gave them; ſome by <hi>Treachery</hi> and <hi>Falſhood;</hi> ſome by <hi>Cowardice;</hi> ſome by <hi>ambitious Mutinies;</hi> and ſome by the moſt <hi>unheard of Debauches</hi> in the whole World; ſo that they eſtranged the <hi>hearts</hi> of the <hi>People</hi> from that moſt <hi>pious Prince;</hi> they made the ignorant think that the <hi>Maſter</hi> could never be <hi>Righteous,</hi> that had ſuch <hi>diſſolute</hi> and <hi>profligate</hi> Servants; that that Cauſe could never be of <hi>God,</hi> whoſe <hi>Defenders carried themſelves like Devils.</hi> They drank the <hi>blood</hi> of the <hi>poor Souldiers</hi> whileſt they <hi>ſpent</hi> their <hi>Pay,</hi> and brake the <hi>Nerves</hi> and <hi>Sinews of the War,</hi> when they <hi>ſpent</hi> it on their <hi>Luſts.</hi> It was therefore your <hi>wickedneſs</hi> too, that brought <hi>CHARLES</hi> to the <hi>Block,</hi> and left Him <hi>naked</hi> and <hi>expoſed</hi> to the <hi>force of his Enemies.</hi> Nay, to this Day, many of you, becauſe you have not the <hi>compenſations</hi> that you expected, have almoſt caſt off all <hi>ſenſe of Religion,</hi> and grown <hi>indifferent</hi> and <hi>cold</hi> in the ſervice of <hi>God,</hi> and in Reverence to that <hi>Church,</hi> which formerly was your <hi>common boaſt.</hi> But my advice muſt be the ſame to theſe, as to the former, and as the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> counſel was to the <hi>Jews: Repent of your wickedneſs, that your ſins may be blotted out;</hi> caſt not all the dirt of
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:95422:20"/>this great <hi>Guilt</hi> on <hi>others</hi> wholly, but take up <hi>your own Load,</hi> and <hi>redeem</hi> your <hi>credit</hi> by new and pious lives; and let it not hereafter be ſaid, that there is one of <hi>CHARLES his Souldiers,</hi> but is an <hi>Imitator of CHARLES his Virtues,</hi> and a <hi>stedfaſt Diſciple to CHARLES his Religion.</hi> Remember that the <hi>Blood</hi> of this <hi>moſt excellent Prince</hi> hath given a moſt <hi>ample teſtimony</hi> to the <hi>Proteſtant Cauſe,</hi> and that this <hi>inference</hi> is moſt <hi>natural</hi> and <hi>undenyable; That if CHARLES be a true Martyr, the Church of England is the trueſt Church.</hi> And, now let us all, without di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided and diſ-united hearts, caſt our ſelves low before <hi>GOD's Mercy Seat,</hi> and Implore his Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don for this Great and National Sin, and ſay:</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="prayer">
                        <p>Deliver <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s from Blood-guiltineſs, O God, the God of our Salvation, and our Tongue ſhall ſing aloud of thy Righteouſneſs. Remember not Lord our Offences, nor the Offences of our Fore-fathers, neither take thou Vengeance of our Sins; Spare <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s good Lord, ſpare thy People, whom thou haſt redeemed with thy moſt pretious Blood, and be not angry with <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s for ever. Let the Blood of Jeſus out cry the Blood of Charles; the Blood of thine innocent Son, expiate the Blood of thy righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous Servant; Make our hearts truly ſenſible of the Guilt of this great Wickedneſs, and reconcile us to thee, whom we have moſt highly provoked; that the Army of Saints, may equal the Army of Martyrs; that our ſinful Nation may no more
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:95422:20"/>feel the Scourges of thine heavy Hand; that our Conſciences may be healed, our Tranſgreſſions pardoned in this life, that we may obtain alſo the Manſions and Felicity of true Penitents in the life to come; To which, God's Grace and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite Mercy and Pardon bring us all, for the Merits of his Son; to whom with the Holy Ghoſt, Three Perſons, and One God, be all Honour, and Glory, World without end.</p>
                        <closer>Amen.</closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
